<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Features</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Hard Token Management Framework Features">
  <p>
    The Core Hard Token Management Framework is a set of API used to simplify
    the development of Token Management applications. It contains:
    </p>
<ul>
<li>a WAR application containing the basic applet</li>
<li>A client installation package for Windows installing the necessary DLLs</li>
<li>API for simple calls to the tokens, such as 'getCertificates', 'changePIN' etc</li>
<li>WS API to access EJBCA for generating certificate, fetching PUK data and so on</li>
<li>API for storing information locally on the computer such as administrator settings</li>
<li>API for logging</li>
<li>A lot of related util tools.</li>
<p> See Development Manual for more details about the API </p>
</ul>    

  </section>
    <section name="'ToLiMa' Application Suite Features">
    <p>
      ToLiMa is a ready made application suite using the Hard Token Management Framework and
      is designed to be flexible enough to fit into several organizations needs. <br/><br/>
      To see ToLiMa in action see the flash demo or the screen shots.<br/><br/>
      ToLiMa currently have the following features:
    </p>
<ul>
<li>Support of Setec 4.3.1 and 4.4.1 cards (TODO check)</li>
<li>Issuing cards with 1 or more certificates</li>
<li>Support for 2 PIN, basic and signature</li>
<li>Contains a 'Card Analyser' that analyses the card for the card administrator to give a suggestion of what is wrong with the card</li>
<li>Possibilty to issue ordinary, temporary and project cards with different validities</li>
<li>When a ordinary or project card is generated is all previous cards revoked</li>
<li>When a temporary card is issued is the ordinary card set on hold until the ordinary card is reactivated</li>
<li>Userdata is fetched from existing user data source.</li>
<li>Possibility to unlock cards without exposing the PUK. The PUK is stored encrypted in EJBCA database.</li>
<li>Easy to renew an expiring card</li>
<li>Cards not used anymore can be revoked and ereased.</li>
<li>It is also possible for a card administrator to do some management remotely (without having the card) such as revoking and activating a ordinary card.</li>
<li>For 24/7 working environments where a card administrator might not be available it is possible for a
colleague to issue a 'card unlock' or 'issue temporary' card request that is sent to a central support unit for approval</li>
<li>TaLiMa also have error reporting functionality where unexpected error can be sent to the technical administrators for analysis</li>
</ul>    

  </section>

</body>
</document>

