<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Contact &amp; Support</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
<section name="Commercial Support">
<p>
<i>Ready-made commercial SignServer support</i><br/>
<a href="https://www.primekey.se/Services/Support">Support programs</a> and other qualified 
professional services are provided by <a href="https://www.primekey.se">PrimeKey Solutions AB</a>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="3rd Party Integration">
<p>
Looking to integrate a 3rd party application with SignServer? SignServer has the most flexible range of standard, and non standard, protocols for seamless integration.
<br/>Contact <a href="https://www.primekey.se/contact-us/">PrimeKey</a> if you need more information or assistance.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Security Notifications">
<p>
If you have a security notification regarding SignServer, please send an email to <i>security at primekey dot se</i>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Contributors">
<p>
The best way to contact the project admins are using email.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Send an email to the signserver-develop <a href="#Mailing%20Lists">mailing list</a> (see below).</li>
<li>Send an email directly to a project <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/signserver/">administrator</a>.</li>
<li>Send an email to PrimeKey at <i>sales at primekey dot se</i>.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section name="Documentation">
    <p>
First of all, have a look at the SignServer documentation resources gathered below 
"Documentation" in the main menu.
    </p>
</section>

<section name="Training">
<p>
<i>Established SignServer Training</i><br/>
<a href="https://www.primekey.se/Services/Training">Training Courses</a> for advanced users are held internationally by PrimeKey and their partners.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Mailing Lists">
<p>
The SignServer project has two public mailing lists hosted on Sourceforge. To subscribe to
either list, or browse archived messages, simply click optional link(s) below.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/signserver-announce">signserver-announce</a> A low traffic
 list about new releases and patches.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/signserver-develop">signserver-develop</a> is used for
discussions of a more technical nature. Almost anything regarding SignServer can be posted on this list.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Discussion Forums">
<p>
 There are also several public <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/signserver/support">discussion forums</a>
 that are used for discussions and requests for help etc. 
</p>
</section>

<section name="IRC">
    <p>
    For direct chat for help and to meet the project administrators join the chat.
    </p>
    <p>
    Connect you IRC-chat program to <a href="irc://#signserver@irc.freenode.net">#signserver channel at irc.freenode.net</a>.
    </p>
</section>

  </body>
</document>
