<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Home</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Latest News">
    <note>
        <strong>SignServer 3.2.0 is now out!</strong>
        <br/><br/>
        <!-- Read <a href="http://www.primekey.se/digitalAssets/2/2334_Product_Release_SignServer3.1.1.pdf">release notes</a>. | --> 
        Visit the <a href="download.html">download</a> section to get SignServer.
        | There is also a LiveCD!
    </note>
   </section>

<section name="What is SignServer?">
<p>
SignServer is an application framework performing cryptographic operations for
other applications. It's intended to be used in environments where keys are
supposed to be protected in hardware but there isn't possible to connect such
hardware to existing enterprise applications or where the operations are
considered extra sensitive so the hardware have to protected more carefully.
Another usage is to provide a simplified method to provide signatures in
different application managed from one location in the company.
</p>
<p> 
SignServer is based on loadable modules that perform various operations.
SignServer has ready to use modules for:
</p>
<ul>
<li>TimeStamp Authority (RFC 3161 compliant)</li>
<li>Signers for different documents: PDF, XML, ODF, OOXML, MRTD (ePassport
    document signer)</li>
<li>General purpose signers: CMS</li>
<li>Validators for documents: XML</li>
</ul>
<p>The modules can be used using HTTP or web services interfaces. SignServer
also contains functions for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Certificate Validation Service Framework for validating certificates using
    CRLs or OCSP</li>
<li>Group Key Service Framework</li>
</ul> 
<p>
SignServer has been designed for high-availability and can be clustered for
maximum reliability.
</p>
<p>
Different kinds of tokens can be used to perform sign and crypto operations:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Soft token using JKS or PKCS12 files.</li>
<li>PKCS#11 HSM tokens, such as the Utimaco CryptoServer, SafeNet ProtectServer
    and Luna, nCipher nShield or AEP KeyPer.</li>
<li>PrimeCardHSM using smart cards.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section name="Open Source Software">
<p>
SignServer is OSI Certified Open Source Software.
OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.
</p>
<p>
The source code of SignServer is hosted on
<a href="http://www.sf.net/">SourceForge.net</a> and all downloads include the
complete source code.
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

